[
  {
    "qno": 1,
    "question": "Employing the body physically for the production and maintenance of physical facilities is called as --------------- ",
    "options": [
      "Asan ",
      "Pranayam  ",
      "Labour",
      "None of these "
    ],
    "answer": "Labour"
  },
  {
    "qno": 2,
    "question": "Trust, Respect, Happiness, etc., are the needs of ................ ",
    "options": [
      "The Body",
      "The Self (I)",
      "The Self and the Body",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "The Self (I)"
  },
  {
    "qno": 3,
    "question": "The activities of the body (in response) are ",
    "options": [
      "Assuming and Knowing",
      "Assuming and Fulfilling",
      "Recognising and Fulfilling",
      "Knowing and Fulfilling"
    ],
    "answer": "Recognising and Fulfilling"
  },
  {
    "qno": 4,
    "question": "‘Seer’ means the one that ",
    "options": [
      "Does something",
      "Understands",
      "Experience",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Understands"
  },
  {
    "qno": 5,
    "question": "Who is responsible for happiness and unhappiness?",
    "options": [
      "Body",
      "Self",
      "Outside situations",
      "Society"
    ],
    "answer": "Self"
  },
  {
    "qno": 6,
    "question": "Human body is an instrument to facilitate",
    "options": [
      " Sensations",
      "Preconditioning",
      "Right Understanding",
      "Assumptions"
    ],
    "answer": "Right Understanding"
  },
  {
    "qno": 7,
    "question": "When we assume something on the basis of prevailing notion, then it is called as",
    "options": [
      "Preconditioning",
      "Sensation",
      "Right Understanding",
      "Natural Acceptance"
    ],
    "answer": "Preconditioning"
  },
  {
    "qno": 8,
    "question": "Behavior on the basis of right understanding and realization is called",
    "options": [
      "Confused behavior",
      "Wrong behavior",
      "Self-organized behavior",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Self-organized behavior"
  },
  {
    "qno": 9,
    "question": "The activity of selecting/tasting is",
    "options": [
      "Continuous",
      "Variable",
      " Uncertain",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Continuous"
  },
  {
    "qno": 10,
    "question": "The power/force for the activity of analyzing is",
    "options": [
      "Desire",
      "Expectations",
      "Realization",
      "Thoughts"
    ],
    "answer": "Thoughts"
  },
  {
    "qno": 11,
    "question": "When there is harmony among the parts of the body, then it is called a status of",
    "options": [
      "Sanyam",
      "Swasthya",
      "Both Sanyam and Swasthya",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Swasthya"
  },
  {
    "qno": 12,
    "question": "Harmony should be maintained between",
    "options": [
      "Body and Life",
      "Self and Society",
      "Society and Environment",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "qno": 13,
    "question": "The statement “all parts of the body performing their expected functions” is related with",
    "options": [
      "Proper upkeep",
      "Self regulation",
      "Sanyam",
      "Swasthya"
    ],
    "answer": "Swasthya"
  },
  {
    "qno": 14,
    "question": "........... is central to the human existence",
    "options": [
      "Body",
      "Self",
      "Physical facilities",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Self"
  },
  {
    "qno": 15,
    "question": "Realization is the activity of",
    "options": [
      "Self",
      "Body",
      "Both Self and Body",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Self"
  },
  {
    "qno": 16,
    "question": "“Seeing the Self by the Self” means",
    "options": [
      "The conscious observation of the consciousness",
      "The conscious observation of the material",
      "The conscious observation of the co-existence",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "The conscious observation of the consciousness"
  },
  {
    "qno": 17,
    "question": "Activities of the body are",
    "options": [
      "Temporary in Time",
      "Continuous in Time",
      "Discrete in nature",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Temporary in Time"
  },
  {
    "qno": 18,
    "question": "............ is central to existence",
    "options": [
      "Body",
      "Physical facility",
      "Co-existence",
      "Self"
    ],
    "answer": "Co-existence"
  },
  {
    "qno": 19,
    "question": "Which of the following does not lead right understanding in the Self (I)",
    "options": [
      "A process of do’s don’ts, in which we assume what is being said without verification",
      "A process of self-verification on your own right",
      "Verification of the proposals on the basis of natural acceptance",
      "Verification through experiential validation"
    ],
    "answer": "A process of do’s don’ts, in which we assume what is being said without verification"
  },
  {
    "qno": 20,
    "question": "Which one of the following is correct?",
    "options": [
      "Self = Body",
      "Self and Body are in co-existence",
      "Needs of the Self and Body are same",
      "All are correct"
    ],
    "answer": "Self and Body are in co-existence"
  },
  {
    "qno": 21,
    "question": "Need of the Self is",
    "options": [
      "Temporary",
      "Quantitative",
      "Qualitative",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Qualitative"
  },
  {
    "qno": 22,
    "question": "The ‘I’ is",
    "options": [
      "The doer",
      "The enjoyer",
      "The Seer",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "qno": 23,
    "question": "The responses of the Self are:",
    "options": [
      "Knowing and Fulfilling",
      "Knowing, Assuming, Recognising, and Fulfilling",
      "Knowing and Recognising",
      "Knowing, Recognising and Fulfilling"
    ],
    "answer": "Knowing, Assuming, Recognising, and Fulfilling"
  },
  {
    "qno": 24,
    "question": "The needs of the Self are fulfilled by",
    "options": [
      "Right Understanding and Right Feeling",
      "Right Feeling",
      "Right Understanding",
      "Cannot be decided"
    ],
    "answer": "Right Understanding and Right Feeling"
  },
  {
    "qno": 25,
    "question": "Which is material unit?",
    "options": [
      "Body",
      "Physical facility",
      "Physiochemical things",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "qno": 26,
    "question": "Which among the following is not an activity of the body",
    "options": [
      "Assuming",
      "Recognizing",
      "Fulfilling",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Assuming"
  },
  {
    "qno": 27,
    "question": "Self organization means",
    "options": [
      "Innateness",
      "Co-existence",
      "Natural characteristics",
      "Form"
    ],
    "answer": "Innateness"
  },
  {
    "qno": 28,
    "question": "The Body is a ............. unit; while the Self is a .................. unit.",
    "options": [
      "Consciousness and Qualitative",
      "Material, Consciousness",
      "Consciousness, Material",
      "Quantitative, Material"
    ],
    "answer": "Material, Consciousness"
  },
  {
    "qno": 29,
    "question": "Which among the following is a variable unit?",
    "options": [
      "Form",
      "Co-existence",
      "Innateness",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Form"
  },
  {
    "qno": 30,
    "question": "............ is done with the help of proper food, water and air.",
    "options": [
      "Protection of the body",
      "Right utilization of the body",
      "Nourishment of the body",
      "Exploitation of the body"
    ],
    "answer": "Nourishment of the body"
  },
  {
    "qno": 31,
    "question": "What is not the indicator of good health of the Self and Body",
    "options": [
      "Feeling of self-regulation of the body",
      "Feeling of happiness and prosperity",
      "Feeling of jealousy, anger and competition for others",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Feeling of jealousy, anger and competition for others"
  },
  {
    "qno": 32,
    "question": "When we try to achieve happiness and prosperity by maximizing accumulation and consumption of physical facilities as our primary and only focus of life, we become ..........................",
    "options": [
      "Anti-social",
      "Anti-ecological",
      "Threat to human survival",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "qno": 33,
    "question": "On having realization and understanding, we get",
    "options": [
      "Assurance",
      "Satisfaction",
      "Universality",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "qno": 34,
    "question": "Physical facilities are required in ..................... quantity",
    "options": [
      "Uncertain",
      "Limited",
      "Unlimited",
      "Insignificant"
    ],
    "answer": "Limited"
  },
  {
    "qno": 35,
    "question": "Doer means the one who ................",
    "options": [
      "Understands",
      "Does something",
      "Experience",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Does something"
  },
  {
    "qno": 36,
    "question": "The basic unit of learning human interaction is ........................",
    "options": [
      "Society",
      "School",
      "Family",
      "Nature"
    ],
    "answer": "Family"
  },
  {
    "qno": 37,
    "question": "In Value Education ‘Sanyam’ means .......................",
    "options": [
      "Self exploration",
      "Self evaluation",
      "Self regulation",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Self regulation"
  },
  {
    "qno": 38,
    "question": "‘Sanyam’ is feeling of responsibility for ............... of the body",
    "options": [
      "Nurturing and protection",
      "Protection and right utilization",
      "Nurturing and right utilization",
      "Nurturing, Protection and Right Utilization"
    ],
    "answer": "Nurturing, Protection and Right Utilization"
  },
  {
    "qno": 39,
    "question": "The pleasure obtained from sensations is ....................",
    "options": [
      "Temporary and source of long lasting happiness",
      "Continuous and source of long lasting happiness",
      "Short lived and continuous",
      "Short lived and temporary"
    ],
    "answer": "Short lived and temporary"
  },
  {
    "qno": 40,
    "question": "We should make choices with external world based on our ..................",
    "options": [
      "Natural acceptance",
      "Preconditioning",
      "Sensations",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Natural acceptance"
  },
  {
    "qno": 41,
    "question": "The Self reads the ................ and gives the ................ to the body",
    "options": [
      "Instructions, Information",
      "Instructions, Sensation",
      "Sensation, Instruction",
      "Sensation, Information"
    ],
    "answer": "Sensation, Instruction"
  },
  {
    "qno": 42,
    "question": "What leads to Resolution?",
    "options": [
      "Assuming",
      "Knowing",
      "Recognising",
      "Fulfilling"
    ],
    "answer": "Knowing"
  },
  {
    "qno": 43,
    "question": "Which of the following is temporary in existence?",
    "options": [
      "Space",
      "Consciousness",
      "Material unit",
      "Co-existence"
    ],
    "answer": "Material unit"
  },
  {
    "qno": 44,
    "question": "Which of the following is ‘ever’ in existence?",
    "options": [
      "Space",
      "Consciousness",
      "Material unit",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Space"
  },
  {
    "qno": 45,
    "question": "Which of the following is continuous in existence",
    "options": [
      "Space",
      "Consciousness",
      "Material unit",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Consciousness"
  },
  {
    "qno": 46,
    "question": "Which among the following in not a characteristic of ‘consciousnesses?",
    "options": [
      "Cyclic development",
      "Temporary",
      "Continuous",
      "Recognising"
    ],
    "answer": "Temporary"
  },
  {
    "qno": 47,
    "question": "........................ wants to live with continuous happiness",
    "options": [
      "Body",
      "Self",
      "Plant and animals",
      "Material unit"
    ],
    "answer": "Self"
  },
  {
    "qno": 48,
    "question": ".................... is just used as an instrument of ....................",
    "options": [
      "Body, Self",
      "Self, Body",
      "Physical facility, Self",
      "Imagination, Preconditioning"
    ],
    "answer": "Self, Body"
  },
  {
    "qno": 49,
    "question": "Find the wrong statement from the following.",
    "options": [
      "Self is seer/viewer",
      "Self is doer (decision maker)",
      "Self is enjoyer (the one who experiences)",
      "Self is an instrument of the body"
    ],
    "answer": "Self is an instrument of the body"
  },
  {
    "qno": 50,
    "question": "Find the wrong statement",
    "options": [
      "‘seer’ means one that sees/understands",
      "All the 5 senses are just the instruments enable the Self to see something from outside",
      "All in the process of seeing, the Self is used as an instrument",
      "You can also see within, without using the sensations in the body."
    ],
    "answer": "All in the process of seeing, the Self is used as an instrument"
  },
  {
    "qno": 51,
    "question": "Which of the following is a wrong statement?",
    "options": [
      "Self if the one who decides – what to do and what not to do.",
      "The body is used to express the decision of the Self, if required.",
      "Self may or may not use the body to execute its decisions",
      "What I think is the decision of my body."
    ],
    "answer": "What I think is the decision of my body."
  },
  {
    "qno": 52,
    "question": "Which of the following is not a correct statement as far as the relationship of the Body and Self is concerned?",
    "options": [
      "It is my Self that experiences happiness and unhappiness",
      "It is my body that enjoys the taste of food",
      "It is my Self that feels enthused and depressed",
      "It is my Self that feels angry and delighted"
    ],
    "answer": "It is my body that enjoys the taste of food"
  },
  {
    "qno": 53,
    "question": "Which among the following statement is correct about the physical facility?",
    "options": [
      "Physical facilities are required to fulfill the responsibility of the Self toward body",
      "Physical facilities are required to keep the body in good health by nurturing, protection and right utilization of the body.",
      "The required physical facilities could be recognised along with the required quantity for the nurturing, protection and utilization of the body",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "qno": 54,
    "question": "What does right utilization of body mean?",
    "options": [
      "Use the body as an instrument of communication (behaviour)",
      "Use the body as an instrument of labour/work, to obtain necessary physical facility for the body",
      "As an instrument for the continuity of human tradition",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "qno": 55,
    "question": "Right utilization ensured of",
    "options": [
      "Physical facilities",
      "Body",
      "Self",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "qno": 1,
    "question": "Transformation of the -------- in nature is more cyclical.",
    "options": [
      "Material things",
      "Plants",
      "Animals",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Material things"
  },
  {
    "qno": 2,
    "question": "Composition and de-composition is the only activity of which order?",
    "options": [
      "Animal",
      "Plant (Pranic/Bio)",
      "Human",
      "Physical"
    ],
    "answer": "Physical"
  },
  {
    "qno": 3,
    "question": "In existence ‘units’ are",
    "options": [
      "Unlimited in size and also active",
      "Unlimited in size, but inactive",
      "Limited in size and also active",
      "Limited in size and also active"
    ],
    "answer": "Limited in size and also active"
  },
  {
    "qno": 4,
    "question": "Space is/are",
    "options": [
      "Unlimited",
      "All pervading",
      "No activity",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "qno": 5,
    "question": "Which order is most fulfilling by the other?",
    "options": [
      "Human",
      "Physical",
      "Animal",
      "Plant (Bio/Pranic)"
    ],
    "answer": "Physical"
  },
  {
    "qno": 6,
    "question": "Natural acceptance:",
    "options": [
      "Does not change with time",
      "Does not depend on the place",
      "Does not depend on our past conditioning and our beliefs",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "qno": 7,
    "question": "Animal order is ------------ based inheritance",
    "options": [
      "Constitution",
      "Seed",
      "Education – Sanskar",
      "Breed"
    ],
    "answer": "Breed"
  },
  {
    "qno": 8,
    "question": "Order of appearance of four orders:",
    "options": [
      "Plant, Physical, Animal, Human",
      "Human, Animal, Plant, Physical",
      "Human, Physical, Plant, Animal",
      "Physical, Plant, Animal, Human"
    ],
    "answer": "Physical, Plant, Animal, Human"
  },
  {
    "qno": 9,
    "question": "Right understanding and relationship leads to",
    "options": [
      "Individual Happiness",
      "Mutual prosperity",
      "Both",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Mutual prosperity"
  },
  {
    "qno": 10,
    "question": "........................ is the human value which is all encompassing.",
    "options": [
      "Trust",
      "Affection",
      "Love",
      "Respect"
    ],
    "answer": "Love"
  },
  {
    "qno": 11,
    "question": "Respect means",
    "options": [
      "Right Evaluation",
      "Right Utilization",
      "Right judgement",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Right Evaluation"
  },
  {
    "qno": 12,
    "question": "One of the following is a complete value by itself.",
    "options": [
      "Trust",
      "Honesty",
      "Love",
      "Gratitude"
    ],
    "answer": "Love"
  },
  {
    "qno": 13,
    "question": "Trust implies",
    "options": [
      "To have the clarity that the other wants to make me happy and prosperous",
      "To be assured of the intention founded on understanding (not based on events)",
      "To see that all human beings have the same natural acceptance (intention) as me",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "qno": 14,
    "question": "Trust = to have the clarity that the other wants to make me.........................",
    "options": [
      "Happy",
      "Prosperous",
      "Happy and Prosperous",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Happy and Prosperous"
  },
  {
    "qno": 15,
    "question": "Each ‘unit’ is ....................",
    "options": [
      "Self-organized in space",
      "Energised and active in space",
      "Recognising and fulfilling its relationship with other units in space",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "qno": 16,
    "question": "There is ................. among all units in space.",
    "options": [
      "Existence",
      "Co-existence",
      "Harmony",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Co-existence"
  },
  {
    "qno": 17,
    "question": "There is a relationship of ...................... in nature.",
    "options": [
      "Mutual Happiness",
      "Mutual Prosperity",
      "Mutual Understanding",
      "Mutual Fulfilment"
    ],
    "answer": "Mutual Fulfilment"
  },
  {
    "qno": 18,
    "question": "To establish Universal Human Order, the starting point has to be ..................",
    "options": [
      "Individual",
      "Family",
      "Society",
      "Nature"
    ],
    "answer": "Individual"
  },
  {
    "qno": 19,
    "question": "Which of the following is not involved in the holistic criteria for evaluation of technology?",
    "options": [
      "Catering to appropriate need",
      "To generate huge profit",
      "To make technology eco-friendly",
      "To make technology user-friendly"
    ],
    "answer": "To generate huge profit"
  },
  {
    "qno": 20,
    "question": "Which of the following is the entry point in the implementation of humanistic tradition?",
    "options": [
      "Universal Human Order",
      "Humanistic Education",
      "Humanistic Constitution",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Humanistic Education"
  },
  {
    "qno": 21,
    "question": "Read the two statements given below and select the appropriate option: a) Right understanding in every individual is part of the comprehensive human goal. b) Prosperity in every family is part of the comprehensive human goal.",
    "options": [
      "Statement (a) is true; statement (b) is false",
      "Both the statements are true",
      "Statement (a) is false; statement (b) is true",
      "Both the statements are false"
    ],
    "answer": "Both the statements are true"
  },
  {
    "qno": 22,
    "question": "Feeling for those who have made efforts for my excellence is",
    "options": [
      "Glory",
      "Gratitude",
      "Worship",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Gratitude"
  },
  {
    "qno": 23,
    "question": ".............. is feeling of responsibility and commitment for ensuring right understanding and right feeling in the self of my relative",
    "options": [
      "Guidance",
      "Respect",
      "Care",
      "Affection"
    ],
    "answer": "Guidance"
  },
  {
    "qno": 24,
    "question": "........... called foundation of value",
    "options": [
      "Love",
      "Respect",
      "Trust",
      "Affection"
    ],
    "answer": "Trust"
  },
  {
    "qno": 25,
    "question": "I naturally feel related to others, when I have the feelings of ............. in myself for others",
    "options": [
      "Trust and Respect",
      "Pride and Ego",
      "Reverence and Glory",
      "Love and Affection"
    ],
    "answer": "Trust and Respect"
  },
  {
    "qno": 26,
    "question": "Harmonious human-human relationship resulting in mutual happiness is the achievement of",
    "options": [
      "Love",
      "Respect",
      "Trust",
      "Justice"
    ],
    "answer": "Justice"
  },
  {
    "qno": 27,
    "question": "If I say, ‘I am good for nothing’, it is a kind of",
    "options": [
      "Right evaluation",
      "Under evaluation",
      "Over evaluation",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Under evaluation"
  },
  {
    "qno": 28,
    "question": "Everything that we see in the nature and existence is the natural expression and unfolding of this",
    "options": [
      "Body",
      "Physical facility",
      "Self",
      "Co-existence"
    ],
    "answer": "Co-existence"
  },
  {
    "qno": 29,
    "question": "............... is central in relationship",
    "options": [
      "Feelings",
      "Trust",
      "Respect",
      "Affection"
    ],
    "answer": "Feelings"
  },
  {
    "qno": 30,
    "question": "The need of human being, i.e., of continuous happiness and prosperity can be fulfilled by",
    "options": [
      "Having a lot of physical facilities",
      "Sensation based living",
      "Understanding co-existence",
      "Having feeling and thought of co-existence"
    ],
    "answer": "Understanding co-existence"
  },
  {
    "qno": 31,
    "question": "How are the feeling and thought of co-existence expressed naturally?",
    "options": [
      "In the form of mutually fulfilling behaviour with human being",
      "In the form of mutually enriching work with rest of the nature",
      "In the form of participation in the larger order leading to undivided society and universal human order",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "qno": 32,
    "question": "Which among the following is not a ‘guideline’ for human values /value education subject?",
    "options": [
      "Universal",
      "A process of self-investigation and self-exploration",
      "Systematic and rational study of human beings vis-a-vis the rest of the existence",
      "Giving sermons and a set of do’s and don’ts related to human values"
    ],
    "answer": "Giving sermons and a set of do’s and don’ts related to human values"
  },
  {
    "qno": 33,
    "question": "Which one of the following is not a comprehensive human goal?",
    "options": [
      "Right understanding in every individual",
      "Mastery over nature",
      "Feeling of prosperity in every family",
      "Fearlessness in society"
    ],
    "answer": "Mastery over nature"
  },
  {
    "qno": 34,
    "question": "The statement “all units in nature can be classified into 4 orders. These units and the 4 orders have definite innateness or self organization” deals with",
    "options": [
      "Understanding",
      "Realization of co-existence",
      "Contemplation",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Understanding"
  },
  {
    "qno": 35,
    "question": "The statement, “every unit has a definite participation in existence and a definite role to play in this existence” deals with",
    "options": [
      "Contemplation",
      "Understanding",
      "Realization of co-existence",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Contemplation"
  },
  {
    "qno": 36,
    "question": "The basic unit of learning human interaction is .............",
    "options": [
      "Society",
      "School",
      "Family",
      "Nature"
    ],
    "answer": "Family"
  },
  {
    "qno": 37,
    "question": "On what basis we can decide our feelings and thoughts?",
    "options": [
      "Right understanding/Natural acceptance",
      "Assumptions (preconditioning)",
      "Both",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Both"
  },
  {
    "qno": 38,
    "question": "Which among the following feelings is not naturally acceptable to me?",
    "options": [
      "The feeling of relationships",
      "The feeling of harmony",
      "The feeling of struggle",
      "The feeling of co-existence"
    ],
    "answer": "The feeling of struggle"
  },
  {
    "qno": 39,
    "question": "To which category a prosperous person belong?",
    "options": [
      "SVDD",
      "SSDD",
      "SSSS",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "SSSS"
  },
  {
    "qno": 40,
    "question": "Authentication is the dynamic activity of",
    "options": [
      "Realization",
      "Contemplation",
      "Understanding",
      "Comparing"
    ],
    "answer": "Realization"
  },
  {
    "qno": 41,
    "question": "All the instructions from the Self to the Body are from the activity of",
    "options": [
      "Selection",
      "Contemplation",
      "Realization",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Selection"
  },
  {
    "qno": 42,
    "question": "What is the dynamic activity of ‘understanding’?",
    "options": [
      "Authentication",
      "Determination",
      "Imaging",
      "Analyzing"
    ],
    "answer": "Determination"
  },
  {
    "qno": 43,
    "question": "Unanimity means",
    "options": [
      "Able to work together",
      "To live with feeling of co-existence, relationship with every unit of co-existence",
      "Absence of ego",
      "Self motivated for fulfilling of the responsibility"
    ],
    "answer": "To live with feeling of co-existence, relationship with every unit of co-existence"
  },
  {
    "qno": 44,
    "question": "Utility value of a unit means, it helps in",
    "options": [
      "Nurturing and protecting the body",
      "In enhancing the capacity of the body for use in societal development",
      "Both",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Both"
  },
  {
    "qno": 45,
    "question": "Artistic value of a unit means, it helps in",
    "options": [
      "Protecting the physical facility",
      "People friendly – Facilitating behaviour (making it convenient for sharing, expressing or receiving knowledge, feeling, thought)",
      "Ease in Use – Facilitating work (making it convenient for usage)",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "qno": 46,
    "question": "There are .............. elements of justice",
    "options": [
      "Four",
      "Eight",
      "Three",
      "Five"
    ],
    "answer": "Four"
  },
  {
    "qno": 47,
    "question": "Undivided human society is the outcome of",
    "options": [
      "Living with justice",
      "Dominating human being",
      "Living in harmony in nature",
      "Developing more and more in science and technology"
    ],
    "answer": "Living with justice"
  },
  {
    "qno": 48,
    "question": "Human Development essentially means",
    "options": [
      "Transformation from animal consciousness to human consciousness",
      "Being the best",
      "Making the nation a super power",
      "Earning more physical facilities/wealth"
    ],
    "answer": "Transformation from animal consciousness to human consciousness"
  },
  {
    "qno": 49,
    "question": "Animal consciousness is ..................",
    "options": [
      "Giving priority to physical facilities, maximization of sensory pleasures and accumulation of wealth",
      "Giving priority to relationship, right understanding and inherent feeling of happiness",
      "Both",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Giving priority to physical facilities, maximization of sensory pleasures and accumulation of wealth"
  },
  {
    "qno": 50,
    "question": "Human consciousness is ...............",
    "options": [
      "Giving priority to physical facilities, maximization of sensory pleasures and accumulation of wealth",
      "Giving priority to relationship, right understanding and inherent feeling of happiness",
      "Emerging more competitive and dominant on others",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Giving priority to relationship, right understanding and inherent feeling of happiness"
  },
  {
    "qno": 51,
    "question": "Behaviour and work are the outcome of",
    "options": [
      "Desires",
      "Thoughts",
      "Expectations",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "qno": 52,
    "question": "Disrespect leads to ..................",
    "options": [
      "Ego",
      "Depression",
      "Acrimony",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "qno": 53,
    "question": "........................ on intention is a major reason for problems in relationships.",
    "options": [
      "Trust",
      "Belief",
      "Doubt",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Doubt"
  },
  {
    "qno": 54,
    "question": "The continuity of plant species is maintained in the nature by ........... method.",
    "options": [
      "Right value",
      "Seed conformance",
      "Constitution conformance",
      "Breed conformance"
    ],
    "answer": "Seed conformance"
  },
  {
    "qno": 55,
    "question": "The basic activities of plant (Bio or Pranic) order are ...............",
    "options": [
      "Selection/tasting",
      "Knowing/Assuming",
      "Recognition/Fulfilment",
      "Composition/Decomposition"
    ],
    "answer": "Recognition/Fulfilment"
  },
  {
    "qno": 56,
    "question": "Existence means ......................",
    "options": [
      "Whatever that exist",
      "To be in harmony with whatever that exist",
      "Unit submerged in space",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "qno": 57,
    "question": "Compassion is the value at the level of .................",
    "options": [
      "Individual/self",
      "Family/Human-human relationship",
      "Society/Universal human order",
      "Nature/Interaction with rest of the nature"
    ],
    "answer": "Society/Universal human order"
  },
  {
    "qno": 58,
    "question": "Kindness (Daya) is the value at the level of ...............",
    "options": [
      "Individual/self",
      "Family/Human-human relationship",
      "Society/Universal human order",
      "Nature/Interaction with rest of the nature"
    ],
    "answer": "Society/Universal human order"
  },
  {
    "qno": 59,
    "question": "If a person neither has the ability nor has the means to fulfill his/her needs, the participation in relation to making available the body is ................",
    "options": [
      "Compassion",
      "Kindness",
      "Benevolence",
      "Generosity"
    ],
    "answer": "Compassion"
  },
  {
    "qno": 60,
    "question": "................ is the sum of the state of harmony within, expressing itself and participating in harmony with the outside world.",
    "options": [
      "Preconditioning",
      "Definite human conduct",
      "Indefinite conduct",
      "Inhuman behaviour"
    ],
    "answer": "Definite human conduct"
  },
  {
    "qno": 61,
    "question": "Methods to remove unethical practices",
    "options": [
      "Audit inspections",
      "Carrying out sting operations",
      "Promoting awareness",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "qno": 62,
    "question": "Which of the following should not be the key question to be answered while planning a production system?",
    "options": [
      "What to produce?",
      "How and how much to produce?",
      "For whom to produce?",
      "How to make/earn huge profit?"
    ],
    "answer": "How to make/earn huge profit?"
  },
  {
    "qno": 63,
    "question": "A good policy initiative reflects................",
    "options": [
      "Conducive to human welfare",
      "Conducive to protection, enrichment and right utilization of resources",
      "Both",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Both"
  },
  {
    "qno": 64,
    "question": "Perseverance means..........",
    "options": [
      "Commitment for living in harmony at all 4 levels with patience",
      "Commitment in helping others to understand harmony and live in harmony at all the 4 levels",
      "Commitment to invest one’s self, body and physical facilities for understanding and living in harmony at all the 4 levels.",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Commitment for living in harmony at all 4 levels with patience"
  },
  {
    "qno": 65,
    "question": "Bravity means ............",
    "options": [
      "Commitment for living in harmony at all 4 levels with patience",
      "Commitment in helping others to understand harmony and live in harmony at all the 4 levels",
      "Commitment to invest one’s self, body and physical facilities for understanding and living in harmony at all the 4 levels.",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Commitment in helping others to understand harmony and live in harmony at all the 4 levels"
  },
  {
    "qno": 66,
    "question": "Generosity means................",
    "options": [
      "Commitment for living in harmony at all 4 levels with patience",
      "Commitment in helping others to understand harmony and live in harmony at all the 4 levels",
      "Commitment to invest one’s self, body and physical facilities for understanding and living in harmony at all the 4 levels.",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Commitment to invest one’s self, body and physical facilities for understanding and living in harmony at all the 4 levels."
  },
  {
    "qno": 67,
    "question": "Self restraint is the expressed value of ...............",
    "options": [
      "Guidance",
      "Gratitude",
      "Trust",
      "Love"
    ],
    "answer": "Gratitude"
  },
  {
    "qno": 68,
    "question": "There is .............in the 4 orders of the nature",
    "options": [
      "Mutual fulfilment",
      "Opposition",
      "Tendency to balance",
      "Struggle"
    ],
    "answer": "Mutual fulfilment"
  },
  {
    "qno": 69,
    "question": "Awakening to the activity of .............. leads to clarity of co-existence and submergence.",
    "options": [
      "Contemplation",
      "Understanding",
      "Realization",
      "Comparing"
    ],
    "answer": "Understanding"
  },
  {
    "qno": 70,
    "question": "Awakening to the activity of ............... leads to clarity of Harmony in nature, Self organization (Innateness)",
    "options": [
      "Contemplation",
      "Understanding",
      "Realization",
      "Comparing"
    ],
    "answer": "Understanding"
  },
  {
    "qno": 71,
    "question": "Awakening to the activity of ............... leads to clarity of Relationship, Natural characteristic or participation in larger order.",
    "options": [
      "Contemplation",
      "Understanding",
      "Realization",
      "Comparing"
    ],
    "answer": "Contemplation"
  },
  {
    "qno": 72,
    "question": "Which among the following indicates the participation in larger order?",
    "options": [
      "Natural characteristic",
      "Innateness",
      "Co-existence",
      "Form"
    ],
    "answer": "Natural characteristic"
  },
  {
    "qno": 73,
    "question": "Which one of the following indicates self organization?",
    "options": [
      "Natural characteristic",
      "Innateness",
      "Co-existence",
      "Form"
    ],
    "answer": "Innateness"
  },
  {
    "qno": 74,
    "question": "Which one of the following indicates submergence?",
    "options": [
      "Natural characteristic",
      "Innateness",
      "Co-existence",
      "Form"
    ],
    "answer": "Co-existence"
  },
  {
    "qno": 75,
    "question": "Which aspect/dimension of a unit indicates its size, colour, density, etc.?",
    "options": [
      "Natural characteristic",
      "Innateness",
      "Co-existence",
      "Form"
    ],
    "answer": "Form"
  },
  {
    "qno": 76,
    "question": "Which aspect/dimension of a unit indicates the impact of one unit on the other unit?",
    "options": [
      "Property",
      "Natural characteristic",
      "Form",
      "Co-existence"
    ],
    "answer": "Property"
  },
  {
    "qno": 77,
    "question": "What aspect/dimension of a Plant change with the time and space?",
    "options": [
      "Co-existence and innateness",
      "Natural characteristic and innateness",
      "Form and property",
      "Property and co-existence"
    ],
    "answer": "Form and property"
  },
  {
    "qno": 78,
    "question": "What is the innateness of a Plant?",
    "options": [
      "Existence + Growth",
      "Cruelty/Non-cruelty",
      "Nurture/Worsen",
      "Will to live in Self"
    ],
    "answer": "Existence + Growth"
  },
  {
    "qno": 79,
    "question": "Which statement indicates the submergence of a Plant in this existence?",
    "options": [
      "Every cell of the Plant is energized in co-existence with space",
      "Every cell of the Plant is self-organized in co-existence with space",
      "Every cell of the Plant is recognizes and fulfills its relationship with other units",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "qno": 80,
    "question": "Contemplation leads to a feeling of .................",
    "options": [
      "Bliss",
      "Happiness",
      "Satisfaction",
      "Peace"
    ],
    "answer": "Satisfaction"
  },
  {
    "qno": 81,
    "question": "Understanding leads to a feeling of ...........",
    "options": [
      "Bliss",
      "Happiness",
      "Satisfaction",
      "Peace"
    ],
    "answer": "Bliss"
  },
  {
    "qno": 82,
    "question": "Unguided self leads to ...........",
    "options": [
      "Obsession for sensation",
      "Obsession for indulgence",
      "Obsession for Profit",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "qno": 83,
    "question": "Existential Law consists of .............",
    "options": [
      "Physical Law",
      "Behavioural Law",
      "Societal Law",
      "All of these"
    ],
    "answer": "All of these"
  },
  {
    "qno": 84,
    "question": "The base of unconditional relationship is ...........",
    "options": [
      "Right feeling",
      "Thought",
      "Expectation",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Right feeling"
  },
  {
    "qno": 85,
    "question": "Right sequence in which Human Tradition can be materialized",
    "options": [
      "Human Education, Human Conduct, Human Constitution, Human Order",
      "Human Constitution, Human Order, Human Education, Human Conduct",
      "Human Conduct, Human Order, Human Education, Human Constitution",
      "Human Order, Human Education, Human Constitution, Human Conduct"
    ],
    "answer": "Human Education, Human Conduct, Human Constitution, Human Order"
  },
  {
    "qno": 86,
    "question": "'Co-existence' is ever present, ever effective, ever ...............",
    "options": [
      "Expensive",
      "Expressive",
      "Extended",
      "Exhausted"
    ],
    "answer": "Expressive"
  },
  {
    "qno": 87,
    "question": "To attain the universal order, which of the following is most effective?",
    "options": [
      "Human Order",
      "Material Order",
      "Pranic Order",
      "Animal Order"
    ],
    "answer": "Human Order"
  },
  {
    "qno": 88,
    "question": "Complete alignment of our view/vision with reality is............",
    "options": [
      "Education",
      "Qualification",
      "Knowledge",
      "Happiness"
    ],
    "answer": "Knowledge"
  },
  {
    "qno": 89,
    "question": "Right Mindfulness means..................",
    "options": [
      "Mind is full of multiple thoughts",
      "Continuous awareness",
      "Remembering things in sequence",
      "Possessing a great memory power"
    ],
    "answer": "Continuous awareness"
  },
  {
    "qno": 90,
    "question": "Justice takes care of our ......................",
    "options": [
      "Physical and mental well-being",
      "Relationship in human interaction",
      "Both",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Relationship in human interaction"
  },
  {
    "qno": 91,
    "question": "Education and health take care of our ..........................",
    "options": [
      "Physical and mental well-being",
      "Relationship in human interaction",
      "Both",
      "None of these"
    ],
    "answer": "Physical and mental well-being"
  },
  
    {
        "qno": 1,
        "question": "What is invariant and universal among all human beings",
        "options": [
            "Natural Acceptance",
            "Understanding",
            "Expectations",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Natural Acceptance"
    },
    {
        "qno": 2,
        "question": "Value education helps to",
        "options": [
            "Remove our confusions",
            "Bring harmony in all levels of human living",
            "Removes our contradictions",
            "All of these"
        ],
        "answer": "All of these"
    },
    {
        "qno": 3,
        "question": "Holistic development of human beings",
        "options": [
            "Living only with Physical facility",
            "Living with Relationships",
            "Living for all the three – right understanding, relationship and physical facility (Human Consciousness)",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Living for all the three – right understanding, relationship and physical facility (Human Consciousness)"
    },
    {
        "qno": 4,
        "question": "Experiential validation of proposal means",
        "options": [
            "Living according to our desires",
            "Living according to proposal after verifying it by natural acceptance",
            "Living according to our expectations",
            "Living according to our thoughts"
        ],
        "answer": "Living according to proposal after verifying it by natural acceptance"
    },
    {
        "qno": 5,
        "question": "Ensuring justice in relationship on the basis of values leads to --------- in the society.",
        "options": [
            "Trust",
            "Fearlessness",
            "Respect",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Fearlessness"
    },
    {
        "qno": 6,
        "question": "Which of the following is more pronounced in animal consciousness?",
        "options": [
            "Right understanding",
            "Physical facility",
            "Relationship",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Physical facility"
    },
    {
        "qno": 7,
        "question": "Identify the correct order.",
        "options": [
            "Physical facility, right understanding, relationship",
            "Physical facility, relationship, right understanding",
            "Relationship, right understanding, physical facility",
            "Right understanding, relationship, physical facility"
        ],
        "answer": "Right understanding, relationship, physical facility"
    },
    {
        "qno": 8,
        "question": "Self-explorations means",
        "options": [
            "Dialogue between what you are and what you what to be",
            "It is the process of self-evaluation through self-investigation",
            "It is the process of knowing the human conduct",
            "All theses"
        ],
        "answer": "All theses"
    },
    {
        "qno": 9,
        "question": "Which of the following fact is not true about profession, if ethics is followed in professional life?",
        "options": [
            "Able to earn a livelihood of the family",
            "Evaluated by the wealth it generates",
            "Requires certain skills",
            "Profession is also a service"
        ],
        "answer": "Evaluated by the wealth it generates"
    },
    {
        "qno": 10,
        "question": "Need for value education:",
        "options": [
            "Correct identification of our aspirations",
            "To fulfill our aspirations in continuity",
            "Evaluation of our beliefs",
            "All of these"
        ],
        "answer": "All of these"
    },
    {
        "qno": 11,
        "question": "Universal human aspirations means:",
        "options": [
            "Happiness and Prosperity",
            "Continuity of Happiness and Prosperity",
            "Happiness",
            "Prosperity"
        ],
        "answer": "Continuity of Happiness and Prosperity"
    },
    {
        "qno": 12,
        "question": "What is happiness?",
        "options": [
            "A harmony state in which you want to be",
            "A state getting through sensations",
            "A state of preconditioning",
            "All of these"
        ],
        "answer": "A harmony state in which you want to be"
    },
    {
        "qno": 13,
        "question": "The basic guideline for value education:",
        "options": [
            "Cannot be defined for the present system",
            "Cannot be universal",
            "Universal, Natural, Rational and Verifiable",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Universal, Natural, Rational and Verifiable"
    },
    {
        "qno": 14,
        "question": "Which one of the following is NOT the part of basic guidelines prepared for Value Education?",
        "options": [
            "Universal",
            "Rational",
            "Leading to disharmony",
            "Verifiable"
        ],
        "answer": "Leading to disharmony"
    },
    {
        "qno": 15,
        "question": "Which of the following is the attitude of ethical human conduct?",
        "options": [
            "Values",
            "Wealth",
            "Storage",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Values"
    },
    {
        "qno": 16,
        "question": "Imagination includes",
        "options": [
            "Desires and Thoughts",
            "Thoughts and Expectations",
            "Desire and Expectations",
            "Desires, Thoughts and Expectations (DTE)"
        ],
        "answer": "Desires, Thoughts and Expectations (DTE)"
    },
    {
        "qno": 17,
        "question": "Which of the options given below is one of the dimensions of human endeavour?",
        "options": [
            "Education",
            "Corruption",
            "Competition",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Education"
    },
    {
        "qno": 18,
        "question": "The basic desire of the human being is always",
        "options": [
            "Happy",
            "Prosperous",
            "Happy and Prosperous",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Happy and Prosperous"
    },
    {
        "qno": 19,
        "question": "Human life is lived at four levels: Individual, Family, ...................., and Nature.",
        "options": [
            "Community",
            "Imaging",
            "Society",
            "Analyzing"
        ],
        "answer": "Society"
    },
    {
        "qno": 20,
        "question": "The definitiveness of human conduct in terms of values, policies and character is termed as .....................",
        "options": [
            "Responsibilities",
            "Values",
            "Profession",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Values"
    },
    {
        "qno": 21,
        "question": "Developing the ethical competence in the profession is the only effective way to ensure ........................",
        "options": [
            "Responsibilities",
            "Ethics",
            "Professionalism",
            "Success"
        ],
        "answer": "Ethics"
    },
    {
        "qno": 22,
        "question": ".................. are considered the moral standards by which people judge the behaviour.",
        "options": [
            "Responsibilities",
            "Ethics",
            "Professionalism",
            "Success"
        ],
        "answer": "Ethics"
    },
    {
        "qno": 23,
        "question": ".............. is the implications of right understanding in profession.",
        "options": [
            "Responsibilities",
            "Ethics",
            "Professionalism",
            "Success"
        ],
        "answer": "Ethics"
    },
    {
        "qno": 24,
        "question": "Holistic production systems are",
        "options": [
            "Eco-friendly",
            "People friendly",
            "Both Eco- friendly and People friendly",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Both Eco- friendly and People friendly"
    },
    {
        "qno": 25,
        "question": "Lot of physical facilities can provide us",
        "options": [
            "Happiness",
            "Prosperity",
            "Both Prosperity and Happiness",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "None of these"
    },
    {
        "qno": 26,
        "question": "The basic capacity of analyzing is known as",
        "options": [
            "Desire",
            "Expectation",
            "Thought",
            "Behaviour"
        ],
        "answer": "Thought"
    },
    {
        "qno": 27,
        "question": "The process of education and right living leads to...............",
        "options": [
            "Labour",
            "Right understanding",
            "Existence",
            "Co-existence"
        ],
        "answer": "Co-existence"
    },
    {
        "qno": 28,
        "question": "The definiteness of behaviour and work of human being is termed as",
        "options": [
            "Human Behaviour",
            "Human Character",
            "Human Constitution",
            "Human Efforts"
        ],
        "answer": "Human Character"
    },
    {
        "qno": 29,
        "question": "Understanding of human values leads to the practice of",
        "options": [
            "Responsibility",
            "Professional Behaviour",
            "Ethics",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Ethics"
    },
    {
        "qno": 30,
        "question": "The second dimension of human being is",
        "options": [
            "Thought",
            "Work",
            "Behaviour",
            "Realization"
        ],
        "answer": "Realization"
    },
    {
        "qno": 31,
        "question": "When we set our goals in right direction with the help of right understanding, it is called as .............",
        "options": [
            "Skill Domain",
            "Development",
            "Value Domain",
            "Prosperity"
        ],
        "answer": "Value Domain"
    },
    {
        "qno": 32,
        "question": "Our participation in different levels in the larger order is known as .................",
        "options": [
            "Behaviour",
            "Efforts",
            "Values",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Values"
    },
    {
        "qno": 33,
        "question": "Attention and Appreciation from others",
        "options": [
            "Can’t be continuous",
            "Can’t ensure continuous happiness",
            "Create dependency on others",
            "All of these"
        ],
        "answer": "All of these"
    },
    {
        "qno": 34,
        "question": "The programme for health and samyam leads to feeling of ............in family.",
        "options": [
            "Prosperity",
            "Happiness",
            "Both the Happiness and Prosperity",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Both the Happiness and Prosperity"
    },
    {
        "qno": 35,
        "question": "Production and work for physical facilities leads to ............ in family and ............. with nature.",
        "options": [
            "Prosperity, Existence",
            "Happiness, Existence",
            "Prosperity, Co-existence",
            "Happiness, Co-existence"
        ],
        "answer": "Prosperity, Co-existence"
    },
    {
        "qno": 36,
        "question": "Education has two domains- Value Domain and Skill Domain. Which of the following is true?",
        "options": [
            "Value domain is the part of the skill domain",
            "Value domain is in conflict with skill domain",
            "The value domain deals with the understanding part, while the skill domain deals with the learning part.",
            "The value domain deals with the learning part, while the skill domain deals with the understanding part."
        ],
        "answer": "The value domain deals with the understanding part, while the skill domain deals with the learning part."
    },
    {
        "qno": 37,
        "question": "Value Education leads human being to",
        "options": [
            "Conflicts",
            "Confusion",
            "Harmony",
            "All of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Harmony"
    },
    {
        "qno": 38,
        "question": "It is the second level of living",
        "options": [
            "Individual",
            "Society",
            "Nature",
            "Family"
        ],
        "answer": "Family"
    },
    {
        "qno": 39,
        "question": "One of the undesirable common habits with us is that we have a tendency to suspect others ................",
        "options": [
            "Intention",
            "Competence",
            "Both intention and competence",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Both intention and competence"
    },
    {
        "qno": 40,
        "question": "Which of the following is not a dimension of human being?",
        "options": [
            "Society",
            "Thought",
            "Behaviour",
            "Realization"
        ],
        "answer": "Society"
    },
    {
        "qno": 41,
        "question": "In the process of self-exploration we will not verify on the basis of ................",
        "options": [
            "Others perception",
            "Scriptures",
            "Reading from instruments",
            "All of these"
        ],
        "answer": "All of these"
    },
    {
        "qno": 42,
        "question": "It is the fourth level of living",
        "options": [
            "Society",
            "Nature",
            "Individual",
            "Family"
        ],
        "answer": "Nature"
    },
    {
        "qno": 43,
        "question": "The result of self-exploration is............",
        "options": [
            "Realization",
            "Right understanding",
            "Both Realization and Right understanding",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Both Realization and Right understanding"
    },
    {
        "qno": 44,
        "question": "The process of verification of any proposal can be useful when verified",
        "options": [
            "At One’s own right",
            "On the basis of reading from the instruments",
            "On the basis of readings from the books",
            "On the basis of others’ perception and understanding"
        ],
        "answer": "At One’s own right"
    },
    {
        "qno": 45,
        "question": "Self-exploration is the dialogue between ‘what you are’ and",
        "options": [
            "‘what you want to be’",
            "‘what others want you to be’",
            "‘what society wants you to be’",
            "All of these"
        ],
        "answer": "‘what you want to be’"
    },
    {
        "qno": 46,
        "question": "Continuous happiness and prosperity are the .................",
        "options": [
            "Impractical thought",
            "Impossible desires",
            "Basic human aspirations",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Basic human aspirations"
    },
    {
        "qno": 47,
        "question": "To be wealthy is .................. condition in the modern world to be happy.",
        "options": [
            "The most important",
            "The true",
            "Not essential",
            "Fake"
        ],
        "answer": "Fake"
    },
    {
        "qno": 48,
        "question": "Being happy ............ good-luck and lot of external circumstances.",
        "options": [
            "Means",
            "Depends on",
            "Does not depend on",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Does not depend on"
    },
    {
        "qno": 49,
        "question": "Which one of the following is true?",
        "options": [
            "A human being needs both, relationship as well as physical facilities. One cannot replace the other.",
            "If a human being has abundant (plentiful) of physical facilities, her/his prosperity is ensured.",
            "If a human being has abundant (plentiful) of physical facilities, his/her happiness is ensured.",
            "If a human being is happy in continuity, she/he does not need physical facilities anymore."
        ],
        "answer": "If a human being has abundant (plentiful) of physical facilities, her/his prosperity is ensured."
    },
    {
        "qno": 50,
        "question": "Living with Physical Comforts only means ...........",
        "options": [
            "Animal Consciousness",
            "God Consciousness",
            "Human Consciousness",
            "Real Consciousness"
        ],
        "answer": "Animal Consciousness"
    },
    {
        "qno": 51,
        "question": "The feeling of producing/having more than required physical facility is",
        "options": [
            "Prosperity",
            "Happiness",
            "Success",
            "Satisfaction"
        ],
        "answer": "Prosperity"
    },
    {
        "qno": 52,
        "question": "To verify the proposal or assumption through self exploration leads to",
        "options": [
            "Assuming",
            "Knowing",
            "Realizing",
            "Preconditioning"
        ],
        "answer": "Knowing"
    },
    {
        "qno": 53,
        "question": "Which are the four levels of living?",
        "options": [
            "Individual, family, society, nature",
            "Thought, behaviour, work, realization",
            "Material, pranic, animal, human",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Individual, family, society, nature"
    },
    {
        "qno": 54,
        "question": "If something is .................. to us, without any force or compulsion, then it is often correct, and does not change with people and time.",
        "options": [
            "Not acceptable",
            "Less acceptable",
            "Completely acceptable",
            "Naturally acceptable"
        ],
        "answer": "Naturally acceptable"
    },
    {
        "qno": 55,
        "question": "The value of any unit in this existence is in its ........................ in the larger order of which it is a part.",
        "options": [
            "Participation",
            "Existence",
            "Performance",
            "Appearance"
        ],
        "answer": "Participation"
    },
    {
        "qno": 56,
        "question": "The four dimensions of human being are thought, ..................., work and realization",
        "options": [
            "Action",
            "Speaking",
            "Behaviour",
            "Performance"
        ],
        "answer": "Behaviour"
    },
    {
        "qno": 57,
        "question": "On continued basis we should examine our ..............",
        "options": [
            "Thought system",
            "Performance system",
            "Belief system",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Belief system"
    },
    {
        "qno": 58,
        "question": "Two basic things in the content of self-exploration are to know my basic desires in may life and the second is to know how to .......................",
        "options": [
            "Perform these",
            "Remove these",
            "Fulfill these",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Fulfill these"
    },
    {
        "qno": 59,
        "question": "Expression of thought is in the form of ............................",
        "options": [
            "Behaviour",
            "Work",
            "Realization",
            "Behaviour and Work"
        ],
        "answer": "Behaviour and Work"
    },
    {
        "qno": 60,
        "question": "Universal, rational, and verifiable are the ................... of value education.",
        "options": [
            "Needs",
            "Outcomes",
            "Basic guidelines",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Outcomes"
    },
  
      {
          "qno": 61,
          "question": "The value of entity is decided on the basis of ......................",
          "options": [
              "Participation in the larger order",
              "MRP",
              "Cost",
              "Physical properties"
          ],
          "answer": "Participation in the larger order"
      },
      {
          "qno": 62,
          "question": "Value education helps us to correctly identify our ................",
          "options": [
              "Goals",
              "Aspirations",
              "Desires",
              "All of these"
          ],
          "answer": "All of these"
      },
      {
          "qno": 63,
          "question": "The purpose of the value education is to ....................",
          "options": [
              "Foster universal values",
              "Make the syllabus easy for the students to learn",
              "Develop values in individuals",
              "Both foster universal values and develop values in individuals"
          ],
          "answer": "Both foster universal values and develop values in individuals"
      },
      {
          "qno": 64,
          "question": "A harmonious world is created by values at 4 levels. These are.....................",
          "options": [
              "Home, Family, Society, Nation",
              "Individual, Family, Society, Existence",
              "School, Home, Office, Temple",
              "None of these"
          ],
          "answer": "Individual, Family, Society, Existence"
      },
      {
          "qno": 65,
          "question": "The content of self-exploration is to understand the desire and ............. of human being.",
          "options": [
              "Potential",
              "Programme",
              "Purpose",
              "None of these"
          ],
          "answer": "Programme"
      },
      {
          "qno": 66,
          "question": "Human-Rest of the nature interaction is called as ............",
          "options": [
              "Behaviour",
              "Production",
              "Work",
              "Realization"
          ],
          "answer": "Work"
      },
      {
          "qno": 67,
          "question": "Clarity and Identification of comprehensive human goals in the light of right understanding is called ........................",
          "options": [
              "Science",
              "Work",
              "Wisdom",
              "Behaviour"
          ],
          "answer": "Wisdom"
      },
      {
          "qno": 68,
          "question": "Comprehensive human goals are fulfilled with the help of ............",
          "options": [
              "Wisdom",
              "Science",
              "Precondition and sensation",
              "All of these"
          ],
          "answer": "Science"
      },
      {
          "qno": 69,
          "question": "To ensure justice from family to world family is called ..................",
          "options": [
              "Production",
              "Science",
              "Wisdom",
              "Undivided human society"
          ],
          "answer": "Undivided human society"
      },
      {
          "qno": 70,
          "question": "Ensuring mutual fulfilment and mutual prosperity from family to world family is .........",
          "options": [
              "Science",
              "Wisdom",
              "Undivided human society",
              "Universal human order"
          ],
          "answer": "Universal human order"
      },
      {
          "qno": 71,
          "question": "Which among the following is not a comprehensive human goal?",
          "options": [
              "Right understanding in every individual",
              "Mastery and complete control over nature",
              "Fearlessness in society",
              "Harmony in nature"
          ],
          "answer": "Mastery and complete control over nature"
      },
      {
          "qno": 72,
          "question": "Ensuring the concept of undivided society and universal human order from generation to generation is called .............",
          "options": [
              "Wisdom",
              "Undivided human society",
              "Universal human order",
              "Human Tradition"
          ],
          "answer": "Human Tradition"
      },
      {
          "qno": 73,
          "question": "Transformation through Human Education includes",
          "options": [
              "Personal Transformation",
              "Societal Transformation",
              "Both Personal as well as societal transformation",
              "Materialistic transformation"
          ],
          "answer": "Both Personal as well as societal transformation"
      },
      {
          "qno": 74,
          "question": "In society, obsession for consumption, profit and sensory pleasure is more due to",
          "options": [
              "Knowledge",
              "Assumption",
              "Recognition",
              "Fulfilment"
          ],
          "answer": "Assumption"
      },
      {
          "qno": 75,
          "question": "Sound, Touch, Taste, Smell, and Form are ..............",
          "options": [
              "Traps",
              "Innate faculty",
              "Sensations",
              "Preconditioning"
          ],
          "answer": "Sensations"
      },
      {
          "qno": 76,
          "question": "Definite completion point of feelings is ................",
          "options": [
              "Outside",
              "Within",
              "Nowhere",
              "Others"
          ],
          "answer": "Within"
      },
      {
          "qno": 77,
          "question": "An individual aspiring for the universal human order will be ..............",
          "options": [
              "More responsible socially and ecologically",
              "More rich",
              "More powerful",
              "None of these"
          ],
          "answer": "More responsible socially and ecologically"
      },
      {
          "qno": 78,
          "question": "“All are our own, all are interconnected and inter dependent” means ............",
          "options": [
              "Oneness",
              "Worship",
              "Ease",
              "None of these"
          ],
          "answer": "Oneness"
      },
      {
          "qno": 79,
          "question": "............... and ....................... are the basis of undivided society",
          "options": [
              "Love and Oneness",
              "Care and guidance",
              "Affection and Respect",
              "None of these"
          ],
          "answer": "Love and Oneness"
      },
      {
          "qno": 80,
          "question": "In Teacher – Student relationship, the teacher should have the feeling of ........... for the students.",
          "options": [
              "Love",
              "Guidance",
              "Care",
              "Gratitude"
          ],
          "answer": "Guidance"
      },
      {
          "qno": 81,
          "question": "In Teacher – Student relationship, the students should have the feeling of ........... for the Teachers.",
          "options": [
              "Love",
              "Guidance",
              "Care",
              "Gratitude"
          ],
          "answer": "Gratitude"
      },
      {
          "qno": 82,
          "question": "For relationship among siblings, there is a need for the feelings of .........",
          "options": [
              "Love and Trust",
              "Care and affection",
              "Respect",
              "All of these"
          ],
          "answer": "All of these"
      },
      {
          "qno": 83,
          "question": "What are the feelings that remain as base of all relationships?",
          "options": [
              "Reverence, Glory, Gratitude",
              "Trust, Respect, Affection",
              "Care, Guidance, Affection",
              "Trust, Reverence, Glory"
          ],
          "answer": "Trust, Respect, Affection"
      },
      {
          "qno": 84,
          "question": "Moral value is combination of ...............",
          "options": [
              "Right Speech, Right Action",
              "Right Vision, Right Resolve",
              "Right Livelihood, Right Effort",
              "Right Awareness, Right Concentration"
          ],
          "answer": "Right Speech, Right Action"
      },
      {
          "qno": 85,
          "question": "Meditation includes .........................",
          "options": [
              "Right Speech, Right Action",
              "Right Vision, Right Resolve",
              "Right Livelihood, Right Effort",
              "Right Awareness, Right Concentration"
          ],
          "answer": "Right Awareness, Right Concentration"
      },
      {
          "qno": 86,
          "question": "Belief centric wisdom is ....................",
          "options": [
              "Knowledge based on listening",
              "Knowledge based on self realization of existential reality",
              "Reasoning based knowledge",
              "None of these"
          ],
          "answer": "Knowledge based on listening"
      },
      {
          "qno": 87,
          "question": "Logic centric wisdom is ......................",
          "options": [
              "Knowledge based on listening",
              "Knowledge based on self realization of existential reality",
              "Reasoning based knowledge",
              "None of these"
          ],
          "answer": "Reasoning based knowledge"
      },
      {
          "qno": 88,
          "question": "Realization centric wisdom is ................",
          "options": [
              "Knowledge based on listening",
              "Knowledge based on self realization of existential reality",
              "Reasoning based knowledge",
              "None of these"
          ],
          "answer": "Knowledge based on self realization of existential reality"
      },
      {
          "qno": 89,
          "question": "Non-violence means not hurting anyone by ..............",
          "options": [
              "Body",
              "Mind",
              "Speech and words",
              "All of these"
          ],
          "answer": "All of these"
      },
      {
          "qno": 90,
          "question": "Liberation means ...........",
          "options": [
              "To see the existence clearly",
              "To see the reality as it is",
              "To be rid of all types of misunderstanding, confusions",
              "All of these"
          ],
          "answer": "All of these"
      },
      {
          "qno": 91,
          "question": "It is natural for ................... to slowly deteriorate",
          "options": [
              "Physical things/Physical facilities",
              "Happiness",
              "Feelings",
              "Relationship"
          ],
          "answer": "Physical things/Physical facilities"
      }
  
  

]